<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>JavaServer Faces Technology Extensions</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="JSF Extensions">
    <a name="background"/>

      <a name="background-background"/>

        <p>This project hosts development of software that extends the
        capability of the JavaServer Faces specification, including
        revolutionary, world class, support for using AJAX and JSF.
        Software within this project is intended to run on any JSF
        compliant implementation, but in some cases the capabilities are
        enhanced when run with <a
        href="http://javaserverfaces.dev.java.net/">Sun's
        implementation</a>, which is bundled into <strong><a
        href="https://glassfish.dev.java.net/">the Java EE SDK</a></strong> and
        in <strong><a href="https://glassfish.dev.java.net/">Project
        Glassfish</a></strong>.</p>

         <p>Similar to the <a
         href="http://struts.apache.org/struts-shale/">Struts Shale</a>
         project, JSF Extensions is delived as separate software parts,
         you can choose to use any combination of them, apart or
         together.  The software is groupd into three areas based on
         when in the software development lifecycle they should be
         used:</p>

	<ul>

	  <li><p><img src="images/new.gif" /><a href="#Design Time">Design Time</a></p></li>

	  <li><p><a href="#Test Time">Test Time</a></p></li>

	  <li><p><a href="#Run Time">Run Time</a></p></li>

	</ul>

        <p>To get the software and try it out, click on the <a
        href="https://jsf-extensions.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList">Download</a>
        link in the left navigation pane, then open the "releases"
        folder and download the "jsf-extensions&lt;VERSION&gt;.tar.gz"
        file.  If you'd rather just watch some screencasts, please check
        out the <a href="slides.html">Slides and Screencasts</a>
        page.</p>

        <subsection name="Run Time">

        <p>JSF and AJAX together: it just works.  JSF-Extensions
        run-time brings the power of AJAX to existing and future JSF
        developed applications.  Included in this software is an
        implementation of the Avatar concept demonstrated by Jacob
        Hookom Ed Burns, and Adam Winer in their <a
        href="http://weblogs.java.net/blog/edburns/archive/2006/05/javaone_video_a_1.html">JavaOne
        2006 talk</a>.  JSF-Extensions avatar is also the best way to
        use <a href="http://ajax.dev.java.net/">jMaki</a>.</p>

        <p>JSF-Extensions run-time also provides a Ruby on Rails style
        flash concept to your web applications.  Very useful for
        master-detail!</p>

        <h4>Live Demo Apps</h4>

        <p>We are happy to bring you these live demo apps.</p>

        <dl>

          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-jmaki/">jMaki, JSF, Standard Components, and AJAX</a></p></dt>

<dd><p>Demo showing the jMaki Scriptaculous In Place Editor component,
Blueprints Scroller Component and several standard JSF components all
bringing AJAXY goodness to your world.  This example demonstrates the
simplicity of using the jsf-extensions AJAX system, just look at <a
href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-jmaki/ShowSource.jsp?filename=/mainColumn.jsp">the
JSP Source</a>.</p>
</dd>

          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-j12/">Jacob Hookom's JavaOne 2006 Demo</a></p></dt>

          <dd><p>Here is Jacob's famous JavaOne demo, ported to use the
          jsf-extensions mechanism.  This example shows how easy it is
          to do auto-complete, dynamic order entry, and many other fun
          things, all with existing JSF components.  In other words,
          with jsf-extensions, you can do ajax with JSF <i>using the
          components you already have and know</i>.</p>
</dd>

          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-ajax-cardemo2/">The Classic JSF Cardemo, AJAXified</a></p></dt>

<dd><p>This demo shows the use of the <code>ajaxZone</code> component to limit the amount and complexity of JavaScript that a page author must write to ajaxify an existing application.</p>
</dd>


          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-dynafaces-getting-started/">The Classic Guess Number App, AJAXified</a></p></dt>

<dd><p>This demo, part of the upcoming "getting started" tutorial, shows
what can be done by modifying one JSP file in the guessNumber app.</p>
</dd>


          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://sunapp1.whardy.com:8090/jsf-simple-partial-update">Simple Partial Update</a></p></dt>

<dd><p>Simple demonstration of DynaFaces partial update capability.</p>
</dd>


          <dt><p><a target="_" href="http://javaserver.org/jsf-simple-events">Leverage the JSF event system from AJAX.</a></p></dt>

<dd><p>This demo shows some of the things you can do when you expose the
power of the JSF event system to AJAX.</p>
</dd>

<dt><p><a target="_" href="http://javaserver.org/jsf-flash/">An implementation of Ruby on Rails style Flash concept in JSF</a></p>
</dt>

        </dl>

        </subsection>
        
        <subsection name="Test Time">

        <p>Sun's JSF implementation uses Cactus, JUnit, and HTMLUnit for
        its automated testing.  We have extracted the testing framework
        from Sun's JSF implementation codebase and now offer it in this
        project.  This is a general purpose testing framework for JSF
        applications.  Sun's JSF implementation now depends on
        jsf-extensions for its testing framework.</p>

        </subsection>

        <subsection name="Design Time">

        <p>Sun's JSF implementation uses code generation to
        automatically create the JSP Tag Handlers and TLD files for the
        core jsf components.  We plan to extract this (or similar) code
        and offer it as part of this project.</p>

        <p><img src="images/new.gif" /> For now, JSF-extensions
        design-time provides a drop-in jar that contains a JSF
        <code>PhaseListener</code>.  If this jar is present in your
        <code>WEB-INF/lib</code>, the <code>PhaseListener</code> will
        listen for requests to a special <code>viewId</code>:
        "<code>/restart</code>" with a special query parameter,
        "<code>password</code>".  When such a request is received, <a
        href="http://java.sun.com/developer/technicalArticles/J2SE/jmx.html">JMX</a>
        is used to stop and restart the application, without doing a
        full redeploy.  This causes all app config files, properties
        files and classes to be re-loaded, which allows for iterative
        development times approaching the holy grail of <a
        href="http://www.theserverside.com/news/thread.tss?thread_id=35538">zero
        deployment time</a>.  <a href="features-zdt.html">Read the
        documentation</a>, try it out or <a href="slides.html">view the
        screencast</a>.</p>

        </subsection>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
