<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>JSF Extensions AJAX Reference</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="JSP/Facelets tags">

<!-- PENDING(edburns): Add ajaxZone tag -->

<!-- PENDING(edburns): Add Facelets tag library! -->

      <subsection name="Scripts Component">

      <p>Convenience component for rendering all the scripts
       necessary for using the jsf-extensions ajax feature.  Place this
       inside &lt;f:view&gt; yet before any usages of the AJAX
       JavaScript objects.  Subsequent occurrences of this tag in the
       page will produce no output.</p>

       <h4>Usage</h4>

<source><code>
&lt;%@ taglib prefix="jsfExt" uri="http://java.sun.com/jsf/extensions/dynafaces" %&gt;
&lt;f:view&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;jsfExt:scripts /&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt; &lt;!-- body omitted --&gt; &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></source>

      </subsection>

    </section>
    
    <section name="JavaScript Objects">
    <a name="JavaScript Objects"/>

<!-- PENDING(edburns): Add examples for each of these -->

      <subsection name="Faces.Event">

        <p>This class extends the <a
        href="http://www.sergiopereira.com/articles/prototype.js.html#Ajax.Request">Ajax.Request</a>
        class from the <a
        href="http://www.sitepoint.com/article/painless-javascript-prototype">Prototype
        JavaScript Library</a> and adds a bit of functionality specific
        to JSF.</p>

        <h4>Usage</h4>

<source><code>
&lt;ANY_HTML_OR_JSF_ELEMENT 
on|EVENT|="new Faces.Event(this, { |OPTIONS| }); return false;" /&gt;
</code></source>

       <p>Where <code>ANY_HTML_OR_JSF_ELEMENT</code> is any jsf
       component or HTML element from which you emit the event,
       <code>|EVENT|</code> is any javascript event supported by that
       element, such as <code>onmousedown</code>, <code>onclick</code>,
       <code>onblur</code>, etc, and <code>{ |OPTIONS| }</code> is an
       optional argument that is a JavaScript <a
       href="http://www.quirksmode.org/js/associative.html">associative
       array</a> supporting the following options.</p>

       <dl>

        <dt><p>execute</p></dt>

        <dd><p>Comma separated string containing a list of client ids
        against which the <code>execute</code> portion of the request
        processing lifecycle must be run.  If not specified, the value
        of the <code>render</code> parameter is used.  If that is not
        specified, the entire view is traversed during the
        <code>execute</code> portion of the request proecssing
        lifecycle.</p></dd>

<dt><p>render</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>Comma separated string containing a list of client ids against
which the <code>render</code> portion of the request processing
lifecycle must be run.  If not specified, the entire view is
rendered.</p>
</dd>

<dt><p>inputs</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>Comma separated string containing a list of client ids of input
elements whose values should be submitted to the server.  If not
specified, all the values of all input elements in the current form are
submitted.</p>
</dd>

<dt><p>event</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>|CLIENT_ID|,|EVENT_NAME|,[immediate]</p>

<p>If specified, must be the only option, and must conform to the above
syntax, where <code>|CLIENT_ID|</code> is the client id of the component
to be the source of the event, <code>|EVENT_NAME|</code> is a JavaBeans
property name of an event method on the component identified by the
<code>|CLIENT_ID|</code> parameter, and the optional
<code>immediate</code> value indicates that the event should run during
apply request values, rather than invoke application.</p>

</dd>


<dt><p>closure</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>If specified, this is a JavaScript associative array object that
will be sent up to the server in the <code>X-JSON</code> header.  This
value may be operated on by the server.  The possibly modified value
will be returned to the client as the last argument in the
<code>replaceElementHook</code> and/or the
<code>postInstallHook</code>.</p>
</dd>

<dt><p>replaceElementHook</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>The name of a globally scoped function that conforms to the following signature.</p>

<pre><code>
function replaceElement(id, content, [closure]);
</code></pre>

<p>This function is called for each component that needs to be
re-rendered with data from this ajax response.  The function is expected
to take the content of the <code>content</code> argument and replace the
DOM element referenced by the <code>id</code> argument.  The function is
expected to invoke any scripts that may be present in
<code>content</code>.  The optional argument <code>closure</code> is
whatever was passed as the <code>closure</code> option to the
<code>Faces.Event</code> or <code>Faces.Command</code> that initiated
the ajax request for this response.</p>

</dd>

<dt><p>postReplaceHook</p>
</dt>

<dd><p>The name of a globally scoped function that conforms to the
following signature.</p>

<pre><code> function postReplaceHook(ajaxZone, innerHTML, [closure]);
</code></pre>

<p>This function is called after the markup replacement for each
component that needs to be re-rendered with data from this ajax
response.  The optional argument <code>closure</code> is whatever was
passed as the <code>closure</code> option to the
<code>Faces.Event</code> or <code>Faces.Command</code> that initiated
the ajax request for this response.</p>

</dd>


       </dl>      

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Faces.Command">

       <p>This class extends <code>Faces.Event</code> and uses the
       Prototype <a
       href="http://www.sergiopereira.com/articles/prototype.js.html#Reference">Event.observe</a>
       feature to cause a <code>Faces.Event</code> to be emitted from a
       specific element in the DOM.</p>

       <h4>Usage</h4>

<source>PENDING(jhook) please provide an easy to follow example of this.
</source>

      </subsection>


    </section>

  </body>

</document>
